Guide to the Charles H. Hapgood Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1918-1979; Series II; 9.39; (26 boxes)
  - Psychic Studies
    - Subject files
      - Temple symbols, undated (Box 34, Folder 659)
      - Tenhaeff, W. H. C., 1961 Feb 26
      - Trance technology, undated (Box 34, Folder 660)
      - Twain, Mark, 1926-1973 (Box 34, Folder 661)
      - Unarius, 1964-1975 (Box 34, Folder 662)
      - Utter, Gus, undated (Box 34, Folder 663)
- Other Papers, 1898-1979; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Eleanor Roosevelt; Teaching Files; and Miscellaneous Papers.
  The series primarily contains correspondence and subject files related to Hapgood's interests outside of his research and writing, in particular a selection of material documenting his concerns during World War II and his teaching career. Hapgood wrote letters to Eleanor Roosevelt on several topics between 1939 and 1960; her replies were not particularly substantive. Their correspondence is filed here by subject.
  The Teaching Files subseries primarily holds reading lists, notes, student papers, and syllabi, and a folder of curriculum vitae assembled by Hapgood. Additional student papers and course materials are filed within Series II, Writings, by subject. The folder with material from Hapgood's United States history course contains the earliest piece in the collection: a letter written during the Spanish-American War by a soldier in the 1st Vermont Regiment stationed at Camp George H. Thomas, Chickamauga Park, Georgia. Its relationship to Hapgood or his family is unknown.
  Miscellaneous Papers contains random material unrelated to Hapgood's research and writings. Also filed here is a photocopy of an autobiographical narrative; although it was in a file folder with Fred Hapgood's name on it, the description of Charles Hapgood within it makes it seems unlikely that it was written by him.
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor
    - American Handcrafts, 1939-1940, 1969 (Box 35, Folder 664)
      Contains mostly carbon copies of letters to and from Roosevelt, likely made before Hapgood gave the originals to the Smithsonian Institution in 1969
    - American Red Cross
      - Loan funds for soldiers, 1944, undated (Box 35, Folder 665)
      - Shortage of nurses, 1943-1945 (Box 35, Folder 666)
    - Stevenson, Adlai, 1959-1960 (Box 35, Folder 667)
    - Miscellaneous topics, 1949-1959 (Box 35, Folder 668)
  - Teaching Files
    - Ancient history, 1952-1959, undated (Box 35, Folder 669)
    - Anthropology, Dartmouth trip, 1959 (Box 35, Folder 670)
    - Curriculum vitae, 1967-1970 (Box 35, Folder 671)
    - Intellectual history, 1950-1967, undated (Box 35, Folder 672-674)
    - History of science
      - Course materials, 1958-1964 (Box 35, Folder 675)
      - Student papers, 1963-1964 (Box 35, Folder 676-677)
    - Keene Teachers College, 1949-1958 (Box 35, Folder 678)
    - Modern European history, 1958, undated (Box 35, Folder 679)
    - United States history, 1898-1957, undated (Box 35, Folder 680)
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Ali, Muhammad, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 681)
    - Book of war letters (idea), 1941 (Box 35, Folder 682)
    - Chinese history, 1946 Oct 13 (Box 35, Folder 683)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1971 Sep 1
    - Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, 1966, undated (Box 36, Folder 684)
    - Eloise, undated (Box 36, Folder 685)
      Contains contact sheet of photographs of Hapgood with a dog
    - Fisher, Scott, undated (Box 36, Folder 686)
    - Human rights, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 687)
    - "I had a dream," typescript, undated (Box 36, Folder 688)
    - Mafia, undated (Box 36, Folder 689)
    - Nelson, Mary, 1979 (Box 36, Folder 690)
    - Paine, Thomas, 1974 Aug 4
    - Perham, Miroslawa, 1974 Jan 5
    - Phelps, Rob, 1972-1975 (Box 36, Folder 691)
    - Provincetown, 1966 (Box 36, Folder 691a)
    - Radio astronomy, 1952 Nov 17
    - Sex, Catholic, undated (Box 36, Folder 692)
    - Wilson case, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 693)
    - Miscellaneous topics (clippings), 1960-1978
- Oversize, 3.34; (2 boxes)
  - Hapgood, Charles (in Series I), 1924-1974 (Box 37, Folder 694)
  - Hapgood, Fred (in Series I), 1968-1978 (Box 37, Folder 695)
  - Hapgood, Will (in Series I), 1968-1969 (Box 37, Folder 696)
  - Harvard University (in Series I), undated (Box 37, Folder 697)
  - McIntyre, Thomas J. (in Series I), 1970 (Box 37, Folder 698)
  - Mailer, Norman (in Series I), 1976 Sep 26 (Box 37, Folder 699)
  - Manhattan Gazette (in Series I), 1973 (Box 37, Folder 700)
  - Rubin, Louis D. (in Series I), 1961 Mar 5 (Box 37, Folder 701)
  - Sanderson, Ivan T., articles (in Series I), 1952 Sep 14 (Box 37, Folder 702)
  - Lee, Ivan (in Series II), 1978 (Box 37, Folder 703)
  - Great Mysteries of the Earth, G.P. Putnam's Sons (in Series II), 1957, 1959, undated (Box 37, Folder 704)
  - "The Little Rhinoceros" (in Series II), 1959, undated (Box 37, Folder 705)
  - Earth's Shifting Crust, correspondence (in Series II), 1961-1963 (Box 37, Folder 706)
  - Earth's Shifting Crust, revisions (in Series II), undated (Box 37, Folder 707)
  - Ewing, Maurice (in Series II), 1960 Feb 28 (Box 37, Folder 708)
  - Rennell of Rodd, F. J. R. R., Baron (in Series II), 1957-1959 (Box 37, Folder 709)
  - Velikovsky, Immanuel (in Series II), 1950-1952 (Box 37, Folder 710)
  - Wilson, J. Tuzo (in Series II), 1963 Jul 21 (Box 37, Folder 711)
  - Arctic Ocean (in Series II), 1954, 1957, undated (Box 37, Folder 712)
  - Bascom, Willard (in Series II), circa 1965 (Box 37, Folder 713)
  - Climate change (in Series II), 1950-1959, undated (Box 37, Folder 714)
  - Earth as triaxial ellipsoid (in Series II), 1959 Feb 1 (Box 37, Folder 715)
  - Earthquakes (in Series II), 1964, 1969 (Box 37, Folder 716)
  - Geomagnetism, general information (in Series II), 1953-1968 (Box 37, Folder 717)
  - Moho (in Series II), 1959,1964 (Box 37, Folder 718)
  - Moon landings (in Series II), 1964 Aug 2 (Box 37, Folder 719)
  - Science, general (in Series II), 1950-1957 (Box 37, Folder 720)
  - Sea levels (in Series II), 1952-1965 (Box 37, Folder 721)
  - Tornadoes (in Series II), 1951, 1953 (Box 37, Folder 722)
  - Maps book, General correspondence (in Series II), 1924-1974 (Box 38, Folder 723)
  - Maps book, revisions (in Series II), 1966 Feb 7 (Box 38, Folder 724)
  - De Santillana, Giorgio (in Series II), 1970 Feb 12 (Box 38, Folder 725)
  - Hawkins, Gerald (in Series II), 1966 Jun 23 (Box 38, Folder 726)
  - Homet, Marcel F. (in Series II), 1970 Mar 22 (Box 38, Folder 727)
  - Mallery, Arlington H. (in Series II), undated (Box 38, Folder 728)
  - Mercator's maps (in Series II), undated (Box 38, Folder 729)
  - Piri Reis map (in Series II), undated (Box 38, Folder 730)
  - Dirksen, Everett, Mrs.(in Series II), 1969 Oct 11 (Box 38, Folder 731)
  - Haber, Jon (in Series II), 1978 (Box 38, Folder 732)
  - Pike, James A. (James Albert) (in Series II), 1967-1970 (Box 38, Folder 733)
  - Franklin, Benjamin (in Series II), 1968-1969 (Box 38, Folder 734)
  - Hurkos, Peter (in Series II), 1964, undated (Box 38, Folder 735)
  - LSD (Drug) (in Series II), 1978 Dec 10 (Box 38, Folder 736)
  - Metelica, Michael (in Series II), 1969, 1971 (Box 38, Folder 737)
  - Prophecy (in Series II), 1975 (Box 38, Folder 738)
  - Psychical research (in Series II), 1964-1976, undated (Box 38, Folder 739)
  - Religious groups (in Series II), 1973, undated (Box 38, Folder 740)
  - Tenhaeff, W. H. C. (in Series II), 1961 Feb 26 (Box 38, Folder 741)
  - Twain, Mark (in Series II), 1973 (Box 38, Folder 742)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt, American Red Cross, Shortage of nurses (in Series III), 1945 (Box 38, Folder 743)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt, Miscellaneous topics (in Series III), 1949, 1958 (Box 38, Folder 744)
  - Teaching Files, Ancient history (in Series III), 1952-1959, undated (Box 38, Folder 745)
  - Teaching Files, Intellectual history (in Series III), 1952-1960 (Box 38, Folder 746)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Einstein, Albert (in Series III), 1971 Sep 5 (Box 38, Folder 747)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Paine, Thomas (in Series III), 1974 Aug 4 (Box 38, Folder 748)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Perham, Miroslawa (in Series III), 1974 Jan 5 (Box 38, Folder 749)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Provincetown (in Series III), 1966 (Box 38, Folder 750)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Radio astronomy (in Series III), 1952 Nov 17 (Box 38, Folder 751)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Wilson case (in Series III), 1977 Jun 4 (Box 38, Folder 752)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Miscellaneous topics (clippings) (in Series III), 1960-1978 (Box 38, Folder 753)
- Restricted Fragile
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 39 contains restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 6, folders 107-110 (Box 39, Folder 754)
  - Box 7, folders 130-141 (Box 39, Folder 755)
  - Box 14, folder 255 (Box 39, Folder 756)
  - Box 14, folder 271 (Box 39, Folder 757)
  - Box 17, folders 328-329 (Box 39, Folder 758)
  - Box 17, folder 330 (Box 39, Folder 759)
  - Box 28, folder 568 (Box 39, Folder 760)